<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Answer to the Earl of Danby's paper touching the murther of Sir Edmondbury Godfrey</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3407</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R980</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11946843</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11946843</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51335</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25591)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51335)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 48:37)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Answer to the Earl of Danby's paper touching the murther of Sir Edmondbury Godfrey</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Leeds, Thomas Osborne, --  Duke of, 1631-1712.</term>
               <term>Godfrey, Edmund Berry, --  Sir, 1621-1678.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="answer">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51335:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE Earl of DANBY's PAPER Touching the MURTHER of <hi>Sir Edmondbury Godfrey.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE pretended Anſwer to the Objections againſt the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> about the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrry,</hi> is ſo far from excuſing him, or making that Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive appear unlikely, that, if the Author be Dr. <hi>Tong,</hi> as is reported, he could not have invented a more certain way to confirm the opinion that Paper is likely to produce amongſt conſidering men, of the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi>'s being the main Contriver of that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſtable villany; for allowing his Poetical flouriſhes, in his Common-place Harangue, about the difference between Proſperity and Adverſity, to be as true as he in frothy Nothings ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s to teach us; and that his Patron ſtands at this time a remarkable Example of Fortunes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ability, as well in being diſſected by falſe and feigned Friendſhips, as expoſed to the furious guſts of Revenge, proceeding (to uſe the Author's own words) from ſuch Foes as his wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Paſſion, which overflowed all bounds of Reaſon, made Enemies to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urple greatneſs, when Ambition got the Reins: And truly Purple greatneſs may that well be call'd, which Dyes it ſelf ſo deep in the Purple Goar of Innocence.</p>
            <p>But to take all matters as they ſtand; Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey</hi> once an active, worthy, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, judicious, learned, zealous and impartial Magiſtrate, now a moſt Villainouſly-murder'd Perſon, which both by the Laws of God and Nature, cries out for Vengeance againſt the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors and Contrivers of his horrid <hi>Exit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> once a flaming Meteor, above our Horizon, pretending by his ill-acqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and worſe-diſpenc'd Power, nothing but ruine and deſtruction to all that Region he had influence on; now a Priſoner to ſtand or fall as his abuſed Prince, and Juſtice ſhall agree: but however undoubtedly liable to an <hi>Hue and Cry</hi> from the Nation, for all thoſe undeniable Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and Crimes he tacitely confeſſes in his Pardon.</p>
            <p>A Pardon ſo drawn up, that were there nothing in the World but that, to point out what is chiefly here enquired for, it certainly would trace us to the Action beyond all Circumſtances yet revealed, but what is right down ſworn of the Murther. For as a States-man merely, and to fence againſt all thoſe trayterous Stratagems of proſtituting the Honour of his Prince and Country, to the deſigns of an Ambitious Neighbour; or his weak contrivance to enſlave us, and rule us by an Army, with other the like half-ſpun, raw, untaking Politicks; a Pardon for Treaſon, Miſpriſion of Treaſor, Conſpiracies at home or abroad, and other matters, with which the firſt and Pardoning clauſe of his was fill'd, relating to matters of that nature, would have been enough: but it is to be obſerved, that the ſecond reciting clauſe of his, ſeems to Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don him all Felonies, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Crimes none but Murdering-States-men, as he is now thought to be, could ever need.</p>
            <p>And it's very likely he ſurpriz'd his Maſter, his loving Maſter, (and, but for him, perhaps the beſt of Princes) into that Pardon for thoſe latter Crimes, by reading but the former part unto him; for it may be doubted, he durſt not read the names of Crimes ſo remote to his Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and from which he could never hope his Majeſty would ſhelter him, by taking all upon himſelf, as he, in his unbounded goodneſs to him, has done for very great ones of the firſt
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51335:2"/>Nature. But to our firſt point, which is, that Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey</hi> is murther'd, and the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> a Priſoner, ſtands ſuſpected of it, which how he is clear'd from, by his Poetical Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate, we will examine.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Paper infers, that becauſe <hi>Danby</hi> could not hope to be much greater, therefore he needed not to do that miſchief: But (to ſpeak the Author's ſtile) that is but a very weak Inference; for Ill men will do as much miſchief to continue, as to obtain Power: otherwiſe <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and other Tyrants, are foully be-ly'd. Then too, he wilfully miſtakes the Paper he pretends to Anſwer; for that intimates the deſign of the Murder likely to proceed from <hi>Danby</hi>'s fear, that Sir <hi>Edmond</hi> ſhould make apparent to the King and Kingdom, as he had done to the Duke, that <hi>Danby</hi> was either the Inventer of the Plot, or Concealer of it, for pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes of his own. But it may be asked, What purpoſes of his own? To this might readily be anſwered, To prevent an Impeachment againſt him, upon one head more, <hi>(viz.)</hi> for keeping up an Army, beyond the time limited by Parliament for their Disbanding: ſince 'tis demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable from his own Letters and Practiſes, that he long before knew there ſhould be none of the intended foreign uſe for them; and if ſo, what uſe could they be continued for but the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flaming of the Nation; or what pretence ſo juſtifiable for keeping them up, as a dangerous Plot amongſt ſo obnoxious and hated a People as the Papiſts, on whom he might be reveng'd too ſufficiently, for the Popiſh Lords voting againſt his deſign of keeping the Earl of <hi>Shaftſbury</hi> (and other zealous Patriots for Liberty) in the <hi>Tower.</hi> Therefore not to charge him with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiring with the Papiſts, as this Paper would fooliſhly hoodwink us with the reaſons ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, are ſufficient to ſhew he might politickly contrive that horrid Murder.</p>
            <p>Next to what is ſaid about the opportunity, is ſuggeſted againſt the Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> by the being of Sir <hi>Edmond</hi> at his Houſe that day, we will, with the Author, allow, that all men who have opportunity, do not cauſeleſly murder their Friends: But it is before ſuggeſted, that he could not eſteem Sir <hi>Edmondbury Godfrey</hi> his Friend, who had diſcovered his malice to his too long blinded Patron the Duke; nor did <hi>Danby</hi> treat him as ſuch, after he had knowledge of that honeſt man's love to that well meaning Prince, in ſending <hi>Coleman</hi> to him; but upon ſeveral meetings and applications to him, revil'd him (though a Gentleman as well born as himſelf) with the foul and opprobrious names of <hi>Rogue, Knave,</hi> and <hi>medling-Raſcal.</hi> And though Murther be ſo execrable a crime, that no Chriſtian can think of without horrour and amazement; yet we find men often call'd ſo, accus'd, and found guilty of it; Nor is there one generous or heroick action in all the notorious life of <hi>Danby</hi> recorded, but on the contrary, it has been a ſummary of baſe ingratitude to his firſt Raiſers, and conſtant Preſervers, of falſhood and injuſtice to his Equals, of tyranny and oppreſſion to his Inferiours, of diſhonour and Treaſon to his Prince and Countrey; in fine, a life of lies and infamies, therefore when provok'd, no doubt capable of any the moſt unnatural villanies: and that this may not be thought a mere uncharitable ſuggeſtion, I will refer my ſelf to the known cuſtom of the honeſt Earl of <hi>Lindſey,</hi> his Lady's Father, who when he heard any notorious Lie, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his Son in Law's moſt notable virtue, ſtill would call it an <hi>Osbourn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to follow our Paper, which concludes on a Suppoſition taken from what is proved by the Witneſſes againſt thoſe already Executed for the Murder, and thoſe, he ſays, have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, he was traced from his own Houſe towards <hi>London</hi> in the morning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> inferring from thence, he could not be at <hi>Danby</hi>'s that day; but if all things concluded thereupon be but as true, as that he was waiting at the Earl of <hi>Danby</hi>'s that day till one a clock, to ſpeak with him, then is <hi>Danby</hi> as ſurely guilty of the Murder, as 'tis ſure that Sir <hi>Edmondbury God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> is dead. For 'tis notoriouſly known to Sir <hi>John Banks,</hi> Mr. <hi>Mules,</hi> and twenty other people of buſineſs that waited with him that day that Sir <hi>Edmond</hi> was there; he complaining then to divers of them how he was fallen into <hi>Danby</hi>'s diſpleaſure, beſides his being there, has not onely been declared to the Privy Council by the Lady <hi>Prat,</hi> but has been atteſted by the King himſelf in open Diſcourſes, acknowledg'd by a great Counteſs, <hi>Danby</hi>'s own Relation, and confeſs'd by himſelf: nor can it be any wonder the Witneſſes ſhould miſtake the ſtory of his conſtant progreſs that day, ſince it is ſo notoriouſly known, they often change their tales of the Rooms the Body was laid in, in <hi>Somerſet-houſe,</hi> during its ſuppoſed continuance there. But to waſte time no farther, it is as likely <hi>Danby</hi> might be deceived in his Inſtruments as other men, if guilty, it is plain have been. But to clear himſelf from ſo probable ſurmiſes and preſumptions which are made againſt him, his onely way is generouſly to wave his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don (at leaſt) till after Judgment, and take his Trial for this and other things charged upon him by the whole Nation: For all ſcribling for him is but waſhing the Blackamore. And it is more than to be ſuſpected, that thoſe who take that pains, or any other ways publickly to defend him, who ſo plainly confeſſes Treaſons and Felonies, by ſheltering himſelf under a Pardon for them, has been ſome of his Accomplices in theſe Crimes, of which, believe it, there will not want Witneſſes, when it is as ſafe and lawful to ſpeak truth, as 'tis now me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious to do the contrary: Which time, ſweet <hi>JES<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> in thy good mercy ſend us ſpeedily.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
